Lester Horton Dance Theater Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Photographic Materials, 1930-1965 (Box 23-38, 71)
  - Photoprints
    - Performance and Publicity (Box 23-37, 71)
      - Lysistrata (Box-folder 24/15)
      - Lysistrata (Box-folder 32/8)
      - Lysistrata (Box-folder 36/4)
      - Medea (Box-folder 25/1)
      - Medea (Box-folder 25/2)
      - Medea (Box-folder 32/9)
      - The mine (Box-folder 32/10)
      - Mound builders (1935) (Box-folder 32/11-12, 71/8)
      - Mirror, mirror (Box-folder 25/3)
      - Miss Salome, bal Caribe 1955 (Box-folder 25/4)
      - On the upbeat, Contents: Brush off blues (BOX: 25/5) Brush off blues (BOX: 32/13) Brush off blues (BOX: 36/5) Chassidic (BOX: 25/6) Kathak (BOX: 25/7) Kathak (BOX: 32/14) Kathak (BOX: 36/6) Pwe bop (BOX: 25/8) (Box-folder 25/5-8, Box-folder 32/13-14, Box-folder 36/5-6)
      - The park [El rebozo] (Box-folder 25/9)
      - Plumed serpent (Box-folder 32/15)
      - Prado de pena (Box-folder 25/10)
      - Prado de pena (Box-folder 32/16-18)
      - Prado de pena (Box-folder 36/7)
      - Prado de pena (Box-folder 36/8)
      - Publicity, general (Box-folder 33/1)
      - Pueblo eagle dance (Box-folder 26/1)
      - El rebozo see: The park
      - Rhythm section. Drum dance (Box-folder 26/2-3, 36/9, 71/5)
      - Stick dance (Box-folder 26/4)
      - Le sacre du printemps, 1937 (Box-folder 26/6)
      - Le sacre du printemps, 1937 (Box-folder 33/2)
      - Salome (1948) (Box-folder 33/3-7, 71/9)
      - Salome (1950) (Box-folder 36/10, 71/9)
      - Salome, 1936, 1948, 1950, 1953, 1955, 1969 (Box-folder 26/7-12, 71/9)
      - Sarong paramaribo (Box-folder 26/13)
      - Sixteen to twenty-four (1940) (Box-folder 26/14, 71/10)
      - Sixteen to twenty-four (1940) (Box-folder 34/1, 71/10)
      - Something to please everybody (Box-folder 27/1)
      - Something to please everybody (Box-folder 27/2)
      - Something to please everybody (Box-folder 34/2)
      - Something to please everybody (Box-folder 37/1-2)
      - Something to please everybody. Pathos (Box-folder 34/3)
      - Something to please everybody. Pathos (Box-folder 27/3)
      - Song of Hiawatha, 1928 (Box-folder 27/4)
      - The spirituals (Box-folder 27/5)
      - Takwish (Box-folder 27/6)
      - Tierra y libertad! (1939 or 1940) (Box-folder 27/7-9, 71/11)
      - Tierra y libertad! (Box-folder 34/4)
      - Tierra y libertad! (Box-folder 37/3)
      - Tinnikaling (Box-folder 26/5)
      - Tongue in cheek (Box-folder 28/1)
      - Totem incantation (Box-folder 28/2)
      - Totem incantation (Box-folder 34/5)
      - Totem incantation (Box-folder 37/4)
      - A touch of Klee and delightful 2 (Box-folder 28/3)
      - Tropic trio, Contents: Batucada (BOX: 34/6) Batucada (BOX: 37/5) Cumbia (BOX: 28/4) (Box-folder 28/4, 34/6, 37/5)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 28/5)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 37/6)
      - Warsaw ghetto (1949) (Box-folder 28/6, 71/12)
      - White savage (Box-folder 28/7)
      - White savage (Box-folder 34/7)
      - Unidentified works (1948) (Box-folder 71/13)
    - Individuals (Box 29, Box-folder 34/8-15, Box-folder 37/7-8)
      - Bishop, Leigh (Box-folder 34/8)
      - Brunswick, Liz (Box-folder 29/1)
      - Covacevicia, Nick [Navaro, Nick] (Box-folder 34/9)
      - de Lavallade, Carmen (with others) (Box-folder 29/2)
      - de Lavallade, Yvonne (Box-folder 29/3)
      - de Lavallade, Yvonne (Box-folder 34/10)
      - Ellington, Duke (Box-folder 29/4)
      - Ellington, Duke (with others) (Box-folder 29/5)
      - Eng, Frank (Box-folder 29/6)
      - Foster, Suzanne (Box-folder 29/7)
      - Finch, Constance (Box-folder 29/8)
      - Gernreich, Rudi (Box-folder 29/9)
      - Gernreich, Rudi (Box-folder 34/11)
      - Goldoni, Leila (Box-folder 29/10)
      - Hanayagi, Tokuyae (Box-folder 29/11)
      - Hill, Jack (Box-folder 29/12)
      - Horton, Lester (Box-folder 29/13)
      - Horton, Lester (Box-folder 37/7)
      - Horton, Lester (with others) (Box-folder 29/14)
      - Horton, Lester (with others) (Box-folder 34/12)
      - Johnson, Janice (Box-folder 29/15)
      - Johnson, Suzanne (Box-folder 29/16)
      - Kadden, Diane (Box-folder 34/13)
      - Katz, Gita (Box-folder 29/17)
      - Kawasumi, Nana (Box-folder 29/18)
      - Koerner, Martha (Box-folder 34/14)
      - Lewitsky, Bella (Box-folder 29/19)
      - Limiou, Jeanna (Box-folder 29/20)
      - Maldonado, Larry (Box-folder 29/21)
      - Maracci, Carmelita (Box-folder 29/22)
      - Meyer, Mary [?] (Box-folder 29/23)
      - Mitchell, James (Box-folder 29/24)
      - Mitchell, James (Box-folder 37/8)
      - Orans, Sandra (Box-folder 29/25)
      - Ratcliff, Carl (Box-folder 29/26)
      - Salkin, Jeri (Box-folder 29/27)
      - Silver, Lilyan (Box-folder 29/28)
      - Trisler, Joyce (Box-folder 29/29)
      - Truitte, James (Box-folder 29/30)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 29/31)
      - Van Cleve, Kita (Box-folder 29/32)
      - Van Cleve, Kita (Box-folder 34/15)
    - Groups (Box-folder 30/1-3, Box-folder 34/16)
      - Dance Theater Company (and others) (Box-folder 30/1)
      - Dance Theater-dancers (Box-folder 30/2)
      - Dance Theater-dancers (Box-folder 34/16)
      - Opening of Choreo 1950 (Box-folder 30/3)
    - Classroom - adult (Box-folder 30/4-7, Box-folder 35/1-6)
      - Workshops (Box-folder 30/4-5)
      - Classes (Box-folder 30/6)
      - Movement studies (Box-folder 35/1-2)
      - Movement study (Box-folder 35/3)
      - Movement study [lecture demonstration ?] (Box-folder 30/7)
      - Rehearsals [?] (Box-folder 35/4-6)
    - Classroom - children (Box-folder 30/8-11)
      - Items (Box-folder 30/8-11)
    - Children - performance (Box-folder 31/1-8, Box-folder 35/7-8)
      - Items (Box-folder 31/1-8, Box-folder 35/7-8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 31/9-11)
      - Album (Box-folder 31/9)
      - Associated captions (Box-folder 31/10)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 31/11)
  - Negatives (Box 38)
    - Performance and Publicity (Box-folder 38/1-4)
    - Individuals (Box-folder 38/5)
    - Groups (Box-folder 38/6)
    - Children - performance (Box-folder 38/7)
- Drawings (Box 50)
  The few drawings in the Collection are an assortment of sketches and blueprints in mediums such as watercolor, pencil and ink, and charcoal. Of note are the architectural sketches and blueprints of Dance Theater by Horton and architect R.M. Schindler and watercolor sketches of dancers performing Horton technique by Verena Ruegg.
  Arrangement is by title or subject.
  - Dance Theater, architectural blue print by R.M. Schindler (architect) (Map-case Map A-3/7)
  - Dance Theater, architectural sketches by R.M. Schindler (architect) (Map-case Map A-3/8-9)
  - Dance Theater, architectural sketches by Lester Horton (Box-folder 50/2-4)
  - Dance Theater, sketch by Lester Horton (Box-folder 50/5-6)
  - Dancers [?] by Lester Horton (Box-folder 50/1)
  - Horton technique by Verena Ruegg (Box-folder 50/8-16)
  - Salome (Box-folder 50/6-7)
  - Workshop sketches by Keith Finch (Map-case Map A-3/5-6)
  - Workshop sketches by Keith Finch (Box-folder 50/17)
  - Unidentified (Map-case Map A-3/4)
- Scrapbooks, 1929-1950 (Box 51-52)
  The two scrapbooks, which cover the years 1929 to 1950, contain newsclippings, programs, photographs, and the like. In particular, scrapbook number two provides thorough coverage of the period 1929 to 1950.
  - #1, 1936-56, Contents: Photocopies (BOX: 51/1) Originals (do not serve to public) (BOX 51/2) (Box-folder 51/1-2)
    Restricted: Do not serve -- BOX: 51/2
  - #2, Photocopies, Contents: pp. 1-7, 1929-37 (BOX: 52/1) pp. 8-14, 1935-37 (BOX: 52/2) pp. 15-21, 1937-41 (BOX: 52/3) pp. 22-30, 1934-41 (BOX: 52/4) pp. 31-37, 1933-37 (BOX: 52/5) pp. 38-44, 1937 (BOX: 52/6) pp. 45-51, 1938-40 (BOX: 52/7) pp. 52-58, 1947-50 (BOX: 52/8) pp. 59-65, 1947-48 (BOX: 52/9) pp. 66-72, 1946-49 (BOX: 52/10) pp. 73-79, 1950 (BOX: 52/11) pp. 80-82, 1947-50 (BOX: 52/12) (Box-folder 52/1-12)
  - #2, Originals, Contents: pp. 1-10, 1929-37 (BOX: 52/13) pp. 11-18, 1937 (BOX: 52/14) pp. 19-26, 1934-41 (BOX: 52/15) pp. 27-36, 1934-36 (BOX: 52/16) pp. 37-44, 1939-41 (BOX: 52/17) pp. 45-51, 1938-40 (BOX: 52/18) pp. 52-58, 1947-50 (BOX: 52/19) pp. 59-66, 1947-48 (BOX: 52/20) pp. 67-74, 1946-49 (BOX: 52/21) pp. 75-78, 1950 (BOX: 52/22) pp. 78-82, 1950 (BOX: 52/23) (Box-folder 52/13-23)
    Restricted: Do not serve -- BOX: 52/13-23
- Business Papers, 1930-1975 (Box 53-63)
  The business papers series consists of financial, legal, and administrative records that document a range of matters both professional and personal. The materials date from the 1930s through the mid-1970s. Of note are papers related to performance and production such as contracts and performers' biographies, internal communications such as memos and notices to company personnel, and school administrative records.
  Arrangment is by subject.
  - Addresses (Box-folder 53/1-6)
  - Bank statements, Contents: 1949-52 (BOX: 56/1*72) 1954-61 (BOX: 57/1*59) (Box-folder 56/1-72, Box-folder 57/1-59)
  - Bills & receipts, 1935-61, n.d. (Box-folder 53/7-14)
  - Biographies/Credits (Box-folder 53/15-20)
  - Calendars, 1957 (Box-folder 53/21)
  - Checkbooks, Contents: 1946-49 (BOX: 58) 1950-52 (BOX: 59) 1953-55 (BOX: 60) 1956-66, n.d. (BOX: 61) (Box 58-61)
  - Choreo 76 proposal (Box-folder 53/22)
  - Choreographic service (notes) (Box-folder 53/23)
  - Contracts, 1928-61, 1971-73 (Box-folder 53/24-25)
  - Dance Theater plans (Box-folder 54/1)
  - Financial, miscellaneous, 1947-49 (Box-folder 54/2)
  - Forms - blanks (Box-folder 54/3)
  - Grants (Box-folder 54/4)
  - Income, miscellaneous, 1940s, 50s, 70s (Box-folder 54/5)
  - Inner City Cultural Center 20th Anniversary Celebration, 1985 (Box-folder 54/6)
  - Insurance, 1950-61 (Box-folder 54/7-11)
  - Internal communications, 1950-60, n.d. (Box-folder 54/12-17)
  - Ledgers, Contents: 1946 (BOX: 62/1) 1948 (BOX: 62/2) 1946-50 (BOX: 63/3) (Box-folder 62/1-3)
  - Legal documents, 1906, 1938-61, 1975 (Box-folder 54/18)
  - Lester Horton Dance Theater Foundation, n.d. (Box-folder 54/19)
  - Loans, miscellaneous, 1950s (Box-folder 54/20)
  - Mailing lists 1 (Box-folder 54/21)
  - Mailing lists 2 (Box-folder 54/22)
  - Newsletters, 1950-53 (Box-folder 54/23)
  - Payroll, miscellaneous, 1940s, 50s (Box-folder 54/24)
  - Production - administration, miscellaneous, 1930s, 50s (Box-folder 54/25)
  - Production - ticket sales, 1930s, 50s (Box-folder 55/1)
  - Publicity - administration (Box-folder 55/2)
  - Real estate, 1930s, 50s, 60s (Box-folder 55/3)
  - Road maps (Box-folder 55/4)
  - Rubber stamps and keys (Box 63)
  - School, 1948-50 (Box-folder 55/5-11)
  - Taxes, 1940-61 (Box-folder 55/12-20)
- Publications (Box 64, Box 65)
  The publications in the Collection are comprised of magazines, catalogues, and books that were most likely used by Horton for research and reference.
  Arrangement is by title.
  - 5 by 2, n.d. (Box-folder 65/1)
  - Album del IV centenario Guadalupano, 1938 (Box-folder 65/2)
  - Capitol news, 1951 (Box-folder 64/1)
  - Dance observer, 1952 (Box-folder 64/2)
  - Dance perspectives, 1963-67 (Box-folder 64/3)
  - Dance techniques and dance mart, 1950-69 (Box-folder 64/4)
  - Design in the theatre, 1927 (Box-folder 64/5)
  - Dictionary catalog of the Dance Collection, Research Libraries of the New York Public Library, n.d. (Box-folder 64/6)
  - Federal theatre, 1936 (Box-folder 65/3)
  - Folkways Records & Service Corp., n.d. (Box-folder 64/7)
  - Los Angeles Music Company, n.d. (Box-folder 65/4)
  - Los Angeles Public Library books on the dance, 1938 (Box-folder 64/8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-58 (Box-folder 64/9)
  - Modern Japanese music, n.d. (Box-folder 64/10)
  - Música y danza, 1943 (Box-folder 64/11)
  - Musique d'orchestre, 1940 (Box-folder 64/12)
  - Musique de piano, 1939 (Box-folder 64/13)
  - Musique vocale, 1938 (Box-folder 64/14)
  - Musique Soviètique, 1938-40 (Box-folder 64/15)
  - New Mexico Indians, 1948 (Box-folder 64/16)
  - Schirmer catalogs, n.d. (Box-folder 64/17)
  - Vincent Van Gogh, a loan exhibition of paintings and drawings, n.d. (Box-folder 64/18)
Sound Recordings
Note: These materials are located in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division (M/B/RS) of the Library of Congress. As available, LC item numbers are included.
Discs
IDB 00558 7 scenes
IDB 00567 7 scenes with Ballabilli
IDC 00010 7 scenes with Ballabilli; Prado de pena
CRL 757280 Les ballets africains
IDB 00566 Batucada; Frevo; Kathak
IDB 00256 Beguine
IDB 00251 Beloved
IDB 00252 Beloved
IDC 00006 Bouquet for Molly
IDB 00258 Brown county, Indiana, copy
IDC 00013 Brown county, Indiana, rehearsal
IDC 00014 Brown county, Indiana, July 5, 1950, rehearsal
IDC 00015 Brown county, Indiana, July 29, 1950, performance
IDB 00253 Cuba antigua
IDB 00568 Cumbia; Medea
IDB 00260 Danzón cubano
IDB 00559 Danzón cubano
IDB 00261 Danzón cubano, played by Hoover & Klauss
IDB 00259 Dedication to Ruth, Mary, Martha
IDB 00250 Dedication to Ruth, Mary, Martha
IDB 00257 Dedication to Ruth, Mary, Martha, performance
VOA 1703 Ella Fitzgerald at Newport, R.I., Jazz J-83/84 [16 in. vinyl]
VOA 1704 Ella Fitzgerald at Newport, R.I., Jazz J-83/84 [16 in. vinyl]
IDC 00008 Empty chair
IDC 00016 Face of violence [Salome]
IDC 00019 Face of violence [Salome]
IDB 00245 Frevo
IDB 00563 Hiroshima
IDB 00254 Hiroshima
IDB 00244 Incident in jazz; Theme for sunday, by Stan Kenton
IDB 00255 Incident in jazz; Theme for sunday, by Stan Kenton; Liberian suite, by Duke Ellington
IDB 00557 Incident in jazz; Mirage; Trajectory; Theme for sunday, by Stan Kenton & Orchestra
IDC 00009 Introduction to the dance
IDC 00017 Introduction to the dance
IDC 00011 Jenny & the bench [of the lamb]
IDB 00561 Just for moving, by Dukey Bard
IDB 00246 Love dance
IDC 00007 The matriarch
IDC 00012 Medea '56
IDB 00247 Medea '56
IDB 00248 Medea, by Nelson Keyes
IDB 00242 Medea, by Nelson Keyes
IDB 00243 Medea, by Nelson Keyes
IDB 00564 Medea, by Nelson Keyes
IDB 00249 Metamorphosis
IDB 00562 Nanigo
IDB 00565 On the upbeat: Brushoff blues; Kathak; Chassidic; Pwe bop
IDC 00005 Prelude; The ruins; Warsaw ghetto, by Sol Kaplan
IDC 00004 El rebozo
IDC 00003 Salome
IDB 00560 La soldadera
La soldadera, Jan. 15, 1950
IDB 00262 [Unidentified]
IDC 00018 Yerma
Open Reel Tapes
Bal Caribe, 1951 [7 in.]
Barrel house, 1949 [7 in.]
The beloved, rehearsal track only, 1948? [7 in.]
The bench of the lamb, 1949 [7 in.]
Bouquet for Molly/Choreo '50 [7 in.]
Brown county, Indiana, 1951, midseason July premiere, practice [7 in.]
Chassidic/Choreo '51, part of On the upbeat [7 in.]
Choreo '52, 1948 [?]; Salome [7 in.]
Dance Theater, March 19, 1951, Kathak? Estilo de tú [7 in.]
Dance Theater, Lester Horton? [5 in.]
RXB 4965 Face of violence [Salome] [7 in.]
Frevo; Batucada, 1951 [7 in.]
Frevo, 4 starts and one full take, practice tape [5 in.]
RWD 8415 Introduction to the dance [10 in.]
Kathak, re-recording, test [5 in.]
Lives of Poe, student workshop, 1948-49? Beloved, 1958? [7 in.]
The matriarch, master tape [5 in.]
Medea, 1951, summer festival, new version [7 in.]
Plumed serpent/Choreo '58, master [7 in.]
El rebozo, 1950, practice tape [7 in.]
RXB 4966 Salome [7 in.]
Salome, dubbed [7 in.]
Totem, 1948 [7 in.]
Unidentified [5 reels] [7 in.]
Warsaw ghetto, 1949, dubbed from disc recording [7 in.]
Xango; Salome part one; Salome part two; Xango, 1950, rehearsal? [7 in.]
Cassette Tapes
RYE 7492 Interview of Carmen de Lavallade by Larry Warren, June 6, 1975
RYE 7483 Interview of Elsa Martinez by Larry Warren, July 12, 1973
RYE 7484 Interview of Elsa Martinez by Larry Warren, July 12, 1973
RYE 7487 Interview of James Truitte by Larry Warren, June 3, 1973
RYE 7488 Interview of James Truitte by Larry Warren, June 3, 1973
RYE 7489 Interview of James Truitte by Larry Warren, June 3, 1973
RYE 7481 Interview of Tony Masarachia by Larry Warren, July 1973
RYE 7494 Salome
Moving Images
Note: These materials are located in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division (M/B/RS) of the Library of Congress. As available, LC item numbers and catalog record numbers are included.
VBM 7281 Camera three. Tribute to Lester Horton, 1963 [3/4" viewing copy, 30 min.]; LC Record #95-511811
FTA 2749 Camera three. Tribute to Lester Horton, 1963 [16 mm archival positive, 1056 ft.]; LC Record #95-511811
FSA 3631 Fandango, 1955 [16 mm kinescope]; LC Record #95-512014
Interview with Frank Eng, July 13, 1995 [3/4" VHS, 90 min.] [copy in collection Box 64]